{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A former member of the Connecticut General Assembly stumbled across a river in this state in 1796, finding a site to found a city along it. That river in this state was described as a body that “oozes rather than flows” by TIME magazine after an incident that helped lead to the creation of its state’s Environmental Protection Agency. For ten points, name this state, the first state created from the Northwest Territory and the site of a 1969 fire on the Cuyahoga River.",
      "answer": "Ohio A"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was nationally confirmed by the Decree of 16 Pluviose after a delegation including Jean-Baptiste Belley arrived in the National Assembly. Leger-Felicite Sonthonax proclaimed this event hoping to gain allies, although it failed to immediately sway Toussaint Louverture. Reinstated in 1848 after being undone by Napoleon in 1802, for ten points, what is this event that began in the colony of Saint-Domingue?",
      "answer": [
        "Abolition in France",
        "answers indicating the ending of slavery in France"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This character disguises himself using Erpingham’s cloak before exchanging gloves with the soldier MicRhael Williams. At the siege of Harfleur, this man delivers a speech that begins “once more unto the breach dear friends.” This king claims that “if it be a sin to covet honour, / [he is] the most offending soul alive” as he addresses a “band of brothers” on St. Crispin’s Day. For ten points, name this Shakespearean king who wins the Battle of Agincourt.",
      "answer": [
        "Henry V",
        "Henry of Monmouth"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this election year, the winning party held its convention at the Chicago “Wigwam.” At the losing party’s convention in Baltimore in this year, many “Fire-Eaters” expressed disapproval with the Dpartyplatform.JohnBell’sConstitutionalUnionPartyraninthisyear,whichalsofeaturedVice-President John Breckinridge among two Democratic nominees from the North and South. For ten points, name this presidential election year in which Abraham Lincoln won his first term.",
      "answer": "1860"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle is commemorated by a memorial complex on the heights of Mamayev Kurgan including the grave of Marshal Vasily Chuikov. A statue designed by Yevgeny Vuchetich is part of that complex and depicts a woman holding a sword. Asger Jorn’s painting of this battle shows soldiers of the German Sixth Army covered in snow. For ten points, name this battle, commemorated by the 85-meter tall The Motherland Calls, the decisive Eastern Front battle of World War Two.",
      "answer": "Battle of Stalingrad T"
    },
    {
      "question": "The North Adams strike at a factory making these objects was broken up by Chinese strikebreakers in Boston. One incident involving this kind of object occurred after Filipino diplomat Lorenzo Sumulong criticized restrictions of human rights in Eastern Europe. Iraqi journalist Muntadhar al-Zaidi threw one of these at George W. Bush during a press conference. For ten points, name this type of object, one of F which was banged against a podium by Nikita Khrushchev at the UN General Assembly.",
      "answer": [
        "A shoe",
        "equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of this woman’s best known songs was written for a 1980 movie she starred in that highlights male chauvinism in the workplace. This woman’s philanthropic efforts include giving away more than 100 million books to promote literacy as well as supporting AIDS research. This musician gained attention in 2020 for donating one million dollars towards Moderna’s COVID-19 vaccine research. For ten points, A name this country singer-songwriter known for the song and movie “9 to 5.”",
      "answer": "Dolly Parton"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s first major newspaper was founded during Reconstruction as the Democratic Statesman and was later renamed as the American-Statesman. Huston-Tillotson University was the first historically black college in this city. Another university in this city was where Charles Whitman opened fire on a crowd from that university’s namesake tower. For ten points, name this city, where the University of Texas was founded. R",
      "answer": "Austin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man claimed that he would have carried out a series of sniper attacks if the book Unintended Consequences was written a few years earlier. Charles Fortier was an associate of this man who distributed copies of the Turner Diaries at gun shows. Revenge for the ATF siege of the Branch Davidian compound in Waco, Texas was one of the key motivations of this man’s attack on the Alfred P. Murrah Building in 1995. For ten points, name this perpetrator of the Oklahoma City bombing.",
      "answer": "Timothy McVeigh D"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man once defined fascism as “nothing but capitalist reaction” and argued that a state of “permanent revolution” was better than a rival’s idea of “socialism in one country.” Seven years after his exile, this man published The Revolution Betrayed which analyzed the Soviet Union following the death of Vladimir Lenin. This man served as military commissar during the Russian Civil War, for which he created the Red Army. For ten points, name this Russian revolutionary opposed to Stalin.",
      "answer": "Leon Trotsky T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man appeased his rivals by issuing the Dictum of Kenilworth. Though this man had been defeated at Taillebourg by Louis IX, Louis supportedFthis ruler against the nobility in the Mise of Amiens. This ruler was captured at the Battle of Lewes by rebel forces, though he was freed after his son’s victory at Evesham against Simon de Montfort in the Second Baron’s War. For ten points, name this father of Edward Longshanks who signed away part of his power in the Provisions of Oxford.",
        "answer": [
          "Henry III",
          "Henry of Winchester"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While this family name wasn’t officially recognized until the 15th century, Henry III is considered the first English king of this House which takes its name from Henry’s French great-grandfather. A",
        "answer": "House of Plantagenet"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This movement’s founder spread his teachings door-to-door in Detroit and Chicago, and this organization holds its Saviour’s Day event on that man’s birthday. This movement’s official newspaper is the Chicago based Final Call. Chicago is also home to the Mosque Maryam, which serves as this movement’s headquarters. This movement was founded in 1932 by Wallace Fard Muhammad. For ten points, name this Black religious movement, led after 2010 by Louis Farrakhan.",
        "answer": [
          "Nation of Islam",
          "NOI,"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After Wallace Fard Muhammad mysteriously disappeared, this man took over the Nation of Islam and later served as Malcom X’s mentor.",
        "answer": [
          "Elijah Muhammad",
          "Elijah Robert Poole"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this battle, George Gay was the only survivor of John Waldron’s VT-8. The efforts of SBD Dauntless dive bombers proved more successful than the TBD Devastators, sinking the Hiryu, Soryu, and Kaga. A forty-eight hour repair of the carrier Yorktown enabled its decisive participation in this battle D after damage suffered at the Battle of the Coral Sea. For ten points, name this turning point of the War in the Pacific, a June 1942 naval victory named for an island west of Hawaii.",
        "answer": "Battle of Midway"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The occupation of Midway was part of an attempt to eliminate U.S. carrier forces, an attempt that was precipitated by this man’s April 1942 air raid on Tokyo.",
        "answer": "James “Jimmy” Doolittle T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s role in the Soka Gakkai Buddhist movement may have influenced him to rename one of the Causeway Islands after Daisaku Ikeda. This man, who ordered the brutal execution of Hugo Spadafora, rose to power with Ruben Paredes after a plane crash at Cerro Marta killed the former leader of his country. Operation Just Cause ousted this leader, who was assaulted with rock music while hiding in the F Vatican embassy. For ten points, name this 1980s-era dictator of Panama.",
        "answer": "Manuel Antonio Noriega Moreno"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Manuel Noriega rose to power after the death of this Panamanian dictator, who agreed to a series of treaties over control of the Panama Canal with Jimmy Carter.",
        "answer": "Omar Efrain Torrijos Herrera A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a letter to Jean-Jacques Rousseau, this thinker claimed he changed his name “primarily so as to cease to be confused with the poet Roi.” [WAH] While spying on Frederick the Great during the War of the Austrian Succession, this man began working on his Philosophical Dictionary. This thinker mocked Leibniz’s “optimistic determinism” in a philosophical satire. For ten points, name this French enlightenment thinker, the author of Candide.",
        "answer": "Voltaire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of Voltaire’s best known works is the History of... this King of Sweden who achieved an unlRikely victory at the Battle of Narva before suffering defeat and being wounded at the Battle of Poltava.",
        "answer": [
          "Charles XII",
          "Carl XII",
          "Carolus Rex"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this battle, an attempt by the Luftwaffe to gain control of the skies was known as Operation Bodenplatte. A city in the province of Liege was home to the Malmedy Massacre at this battle. The German goal of this battle was to reach north Belgium through the Ardennes Forest. A response to an ultimatum consisting only of the word “Nuts” occurred at, for ten points, what 1944 World War Two battle popularly named for an anomaly in the German lines? D",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Bulge",
          "Ardennes Counteroffensive prior to mention"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of the Bulge began as a German effort to capture this north Belgian city with a prominent diamond industry that was the Low Country capital of the Dutch Revolt in the 17th century.",
        "answer": "Antwerp T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country, the Balibo Five were killed while reporting on a conflict here. This country was invaded in Operation Lotus, though the outcome of that conflict was reversed by a 1999 referendum held by B.J. Habibie. This country was the site of an incident in which Max Stahl filmed the massacre of civilians in a graveyard in Santa Cruz. Shortly after it left Portuguese control, this country’s FRETELIN F government was deposed. For ten points, name this island country, occupied by Indonesia from 1975 to 1999.",
        "answer": [
          "Democratic Republic of Timor-Leste",
          "East Timor"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "According to the East Timorese creation myth, one of these animals created the island to repay a boy who helped when the animal was sick. Thus, the island is shaped like one of these animals, in the same order as gharials and caimans.",
        "answer": "Crocodile A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The phrase “Kollaa will hold” originated during this war in which one side employed an encirclement strategy known as motti. A year after the conclusion of this conflict, the two central countries began the Continuation War. The Vainamoinen was a coastal defense vessel used by one navy during this war in which one side was commanded by Gustaf Mannerheim. Lasting from 1939 to 1940, for ten points, name this conflict that began with the Soviet invasion of Finland.",
        "answer": "Winter War R"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Much of the fighting in the Winter War took place in Karelia, north of this lake that came under Russian control after the war and is today the largest lake located entirely in Europe.",
        "answer": "Lake Ladoga"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Wyoming",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital named after a Native American tribe slaughtered in the Sand Creek Massacre F",
          "answer": "Cheyenne"
        },
        {
          "question": "First national park, home to “Old Faithful”",
          "answer": "Yellowstone National Park"
        },
        {
          "question": "Congressman who represented Wyoming and served as Vice President under George W. Bush",
          "answer": "Richard “Dick” Cheney A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gay man who was tied to a fence and left to die in 1998, the subject of the play The Laramie Project",
          "answer": "Matthew Shepard"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trail named for a Wyoming pioneer that connected the Oregon Trail to new settlements in Wyoming and Montana",
          "answer": "Bozeman Trail"
        },
        {
          "question": "Four year war in Wyoming between large ranchers and new settlers suspected of rustling R",
          "answer": [
            "Johnson County War",
            "War on Powder River",
            "Wyoming Range War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Oglala Sioux chief who names a war ended by the Treaty of Fort Laramie signed after Fetterman’s Last Stand",
          "answer": [
            "Red Cloud",
            "Mahpiya Luta"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Crimea",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Darius I of this empire expanded his power to Crimea in the 6th century BC F",
          "answer": [
            "Persian Empire",
            "Achaemenid Empire"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "People who established a Khanate on Crimea, deported by the Soviet Union in World War Two",
          "answer": "Tatars"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian leader who annexed Crimea in 2014 before invading parts of eastern Ukraine",
          "answer": "Vladimir Putin A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crimean War battle that involved the “Charge of the Light Brigade”",
          "answer": "Battle of Balaclava"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian statesman and lover of Catherine the Great who annexed Crimea in 1783",
          "answer": "Grigory Potemkin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Main base of the Russian Black Sea Fleet, besieged during the Crimean War and World War Two",
          "answer": "Sevastopol R"
        },
        {
          "question": "City today known as Feodosia, a Genoese trading post from which the Black Plague entered Europe",
          "answer": "Caffa"
        },
        {
          "question": "General during the Russian Civil War whose last organized White forces on the southern front operated from Crimea",
          "answer": "Pyotr Wrangel D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Australia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that colonized Australia who also colonized South Africa and the American colonies F",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom",
            "Great Britain,"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Largest Australian city that was founded around Botany Bay and today contains a namesake Opera House",
          "answer": "Sydney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Monarch after whom two Australian states were named A",
          "answer": "Victoria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explorer who charted the eastern coast of the country while commanding the Endeavour",
          "answer": "James Cook"
        },
        {
          "question": "Material sought near Kalgoorlie in the 1890s, leading to rapid population growth in Western Australia",
          "answer": "Gold"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island south of Australia discovered by Dutch explorer Anthony van Diemen R",
          "answer": "Tasmania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor of New South Wales who was deposed in the Rum Rebellion, the only coup in Australian history",
          "answer": "William Bligh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explorer who completed the first circumnavigation of Australia on the Investigator",
          "answer": "Matthew Flinders D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s aide, John Armstrong, was discovered to have been plotting the Newburgh Conspiracy to launch a military coup. In anoFther plot, this man was forced to issue an apology for supporting the Conway (20 pts)",
        "Cabal’s attempts to unseat George Washington. This man’s reputation was ruined after Johann de Kalb was killed under his command at (10 pts)",
        "Camden. This man had earlier risen to prominence after forcing John Burgoyne’s surrender. For ten points, identify this general of the Continental Army who was victorious at Saratoga."
      ],
      "answer": "Horatio Gates"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This woman’s lover, Alexei Razumovsky, was nicknamed the “Night Emperor,” and she A is known for not executing a single person during her reign. This woman was described as the “Messalina of the North” by a rival monarch whom she fought in the (20 pts)",
        "Seven Years’ War. This woman’s reign saw many architectural projects including the near completion of a project criticized for “gilded squalor,” the Winter Palace. This woman took power by (10 pts)",
        "overthrowing Ivan VI in a coup after the death of Empress Anna. For ten points, name this daughter of Peter the Great, an Empress of Russia who was succeeded by Peter III."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Elizabeth Petrovna",
        "Yelizaveta 3RGilbert Ellis suspected the namesake of this city of plotting to declare a king to be sane. The first African American real estate firm, Ideal Realty, was founded in this city. In 1781, Thomas Nelson, Jr. and Benjamin Harrison V fled to this city, which was targeted by + Banastre Tarleton, forcing Jack Jouett to make a midnight ride to save the Patriots. The Rotunda at the University of * Virginia is located in this city, where protests were held to oppose removal of a Robert E. Lee statue. For ten points, name this city where in 2017 counter protestors were attacked by a car driver during the Unite the Right rally. ANSWER: Charlottesville, Virginia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This political party was founded in 1912 by John Langalibalele Dube and presided over the Marikana massacre of 34 striking miners. This party passed “floor crossing” legislation which allowed MPs to take their seat to a different party. Andrew (20 pts)",
        "Feinstein resigned when this party moved against a probe of the Arms Deal. The military arm of this party, Spear of the Nation, was founded after the (10 pts)",
        "Sharpeville massacre. In 2017, leadership of this party was granted to Cyril Ramaphosa. For ten points, name this party that has led its nation since Nelson Mandela became President of South Africa."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "African National Congress",
        "ANC T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Engineer Roger Boisjoly said that this person was the only public figure to support his ominous warnings. General Donald Kutyna revealed that this person discretely told him about failing O-rings on the (20 pts)",
        "Challenger Space Shuttle. This person was part of NASA Astronaut Group 9 and helped develop the “Canadarm” robot. Facing many intrusive F questions from the press such as “Will the flight affect your internal organs?” this astronaut became the first (10 pts)",
        "American to do what Valentina Tereshkova accomplished. For ten points, name this first American woman in space."
      ],
      "answer": "Sally Ride"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Miles Lampson convinced a holder of this position to allow a party he opposed take power between 1942 and 1944. The sister of a holder of this position became the first wife A of Mohammad (20 pts)",
        "Reza Shah. The Second Italo-Abyssinian War contributed to one holder of this position signing a 1936 treaty in his Zaafarana Palace. That holder of this position was preceded and succeeded by men named (10 pts)",
        "Fouad. A 1952 revolution saw the Free Officers Movement overthrow one holder of this position named Farouk. For ten points, name this royal position that was first claimed by Sultan Fouad I in 1922."
      ],
      "answer": "King of Egypt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one scene in this film the protagonist asks another man why he doesn’t seem alarmed toRwhich that man replies “would it help?” A scene in this film sees the protagonist meet Wolfgang Vogel to discuss the arrest of an American student named (20 pts)",
        "Frederic Pryor. The title of this film comes from a climactic scene occurring above the Havel River. The main character is an insurance lawyer tasked with defending a Russian captive named (10 pts)",
        "Rudolf Abel. Based on a book by Giles Whittell and ending with a prisoner exchange involving Francis Gary Powers, for ten points, name this 2015 Cold War film starring Tom Hanks."
      ],
      "answer": "Bridge of Spies D"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The details of this event were almost certainly planned at the Little Green House on K Street. This event was made possible after its perpetrator had acquired property from Edwin (20 pts)",
        "Denby. Congress’s power to compel testimony was confirmed when the case McGrain v. Daugherty arose from this event. The first cabinet member to go to jail was imprisoned as a result of this event, because he had leased the Elk Hills at cut-rate prices in exchange for bribes. That man was Secretary of the (10 pts)",
        "Interior Albert Fall. For ten points, Navy oil reserves were the subject of what 1922 scandal that befell the Harding administration?"
      ],
      "answer": "Teapot Dome scandal T"
    }
  ]
}